Iran needs a lever that doesn't involve
blowing [\h__\h] up, okay? [music] And they
feel they need it because who would
trust a piece of paper with Donald
Trump's or or Netanyahu's signature? I
mean, seriously. People talk about, you
know, "Well, we'll just agree to not
attack them." What the [\h__\h] are you
talking about? You literally attacked
them while negotiating with them, okay?
On the AI front, Anthropic has this new
model. They haven't released it because
it's so dangerous. Some people say this
is marketing hype. I think mainly it's
not, I'm afraid. And I would imagine
that even a lone bad actor or small
rogue group could do real damage. This
is one reason [music] this stuff has to
be governed internationally. So, my
proposal is turn this around instead of
saying we have to [music] address AI on
an international level because of these
threats, let's do a positive vision.
Let's work together on an AI project
that would solve things that we're
currently not able to solve very
effectively such as there are all these
wars [music] going on. And it seems to
me that mediation can be solved
algorithmically.
Hello, Nikita.
Hey, Bob. How are you doing? Not too
bad. Let me introduce us. I'm Robert
Wright, publisher of Nonzero Newsletter.
This is the Nonzero Podcast. You're
Nikita Petrov,
well-known member of Nonzero team, also
proprietor of the Psychopolitica
Substack Newsletter, well worth checking
out.
And I bring good news to the world.
Uh, you have a world-saving idea that
cuts across AI and war
uh, in in a constructive way, which is
good cuz there's been some,
uh, you know, kind of alarming news on
both fronts lately. People are probably
familiar with the Iran war. They're
probably familiar with this big missile
thing that came out of, uh, Anthropic's
AI lab. In any event, we'll catch people
up on that. But I just want to say I
just want to thank you in advance,
Nikita, for having the idea that's going
to save
the world.
Somebody has to, right? Yeah. And, you
know, a lot of people like they're so
busy like, uh, climbing the career
ladder, making money.
But you, you're not making any money.
You're not making any progress on the
career ladder. So,
you got a lot of time on your hands,
right? I'm in the south of Spain and I
have a dog that needs walking. So, I
spend a lot of my time walking in the
sun in the, uh, streets of Malaga.
There's nothing to do but think about
world-saving ideas. You don't listen to
podcasts while you walk your dog?
I don't have many that I listen to
anymore. Like I I'm I got tired of most
of them. And audiobooks, I get
distracted too easily. Like with
podcasts you can zone out a little bit.
I don't know that what it is about the
density of information. But with an
audiobook,
like I get distracted and then I miss
half a page and that's not okay.
Actually, toward the end of this
conversation, maybe I can talk about a
couple of audiobooks I've either
finished or I'm in the middle of,
uh, one on John Adams, one on Adolf
Hitler.
Um, and one on Demis Hassabis, Really
combo.
uh, the head of Google DeepMind. So, um,
yeah, let me catch people up on recent
events in these two relevant realms.
First of all, as probably everybody
knows, Trump
after spending,
uh, you know, I don't know, 18 hours of
negotiation that took the Obama
administration like 18 years of
negotiation to solve, um, Trump kind of
acted as if he'd given up and it was
over and J.D. Vance was like, uh, you
know, we put our offer on the table, let
us know whether you accept or decline.
Um, and then, uh, Trump imposed a
blockade,
uh, on Iranian ports, which, of course,
is an act of war. Nothing unusual, uh,
about, uh,
waging war on Iran, but this was during
a ceasefire. Um, and Iran made alarming,
uh, noises about how they would respond
to that by basically making other ports
in the area inoperable, which is, you
know, probably a euphemism.
Then a couple of things happened that I
think account for the fact that the
price of oil is not higher than it is
now. As of when we started taping, it
was, uh,
I don't know,
you [clears throat] know, high 90s, but
not as high as it had been, not as high
as you might think,
uh, given given the news that, you know,
Trump was saying, "Well, we're going to
make sure the Strait of [laughter]
Hormuz is closed. That'll show Iran not
not to close it." Um,
the,
uh,
and I think the developments are, I
don't know. First of all, there was a
report that Saudi Arabia was urging
Trump to rethink the, uh, the the
blockade. I wonder if that story was
leaked to reassure markets. I don't
know. There was also a story that could
have been leaked to make negotiations
more soluble than people might have
thought. And that was the news that, um,
according to this New York Times story
at least, the big remaining issue was,
uh, Trump wanted
Iran to flat out suspend enrichment at
any level,
uh, for 20 years. Iran was willing to go
5 years. And And I think people thought,
"Well, maybe they can work that out.
Maybe they can compromise on that,
right?" Now, I don't think that is the
only remaining issue, but, uh, in any
event,
uh, that may account for, um, the, uh,
you know, the relatively cheerful mood
of the markets as far as I can tell.
The, I should say,
uh, you know, this idea of no enrichment
at all
would be new. What the Obama deal had
done was say you can enrich at a very
low level, like 3% or something.
But you're going to be so
comprehensively monitored and inspected
that we will know exactly what you're
doing. If you suddenly decided to break
out and try to get a nuclear weapon, it
would take you, you know, months and
months to get the weapons-grade uranium,
more months to turn it into weapon. Be
plenty of time for, you know, Israel to
do what it would inevitably do under
those circumstances. In fact,
uh, you wouldn't you wouldn't need that
much time. But that was the idea. So,
uh, and I assume the Trump deal would
include that
beyond any period of flat, you know, a
flat-out moratorium on any kind of
enrichment, which again would be a new
concession
on Iran's part. Okay, so there's that.
That's where we are on that. Um,
I saw a headline. Did you see this? Am I
Am I getting this right that there was a
Chinese, uh, ship that went through the
strait after Trump, uh, announced the
blockade?
I was that like a a day or two ago?
Uh, the story I saw was like 7 hours
ago, but it references Bloomberg. Let me
see. April 14.
Yeah, so it's like
12 hours ago, I guess. Do you know if it
was going in or coming out?
Uh, um, I will [clears throat] say that,
uh, through in a clarification of the
blockade, I think the Trump
administration said,
"Well, if they want to go to the Strait
of Hormuz to a non-Iranian port,
we'll permit that or come out from one."
I I believe. So, that could account for
I No, I have not heard that report. I
did hear that a,
uh, maybe an Iranian either an Iranian
kind of related tanker either coming
from the from an Iranian port or maybe
maybe flat out
Iranian or something
had turned back had started to come out
and turned back in the face of the
blockade. So, they were respecting the
blockade
for the time being.
Um, What I saw that headline what may it
made me think is enforcement. Like when
Iran closes the strait, Iran is already
at war, it's bombing neighboring
countries, it is a logical step like to
say we're going to, you know, shoot or
bomb or whatever
at, uh, a ship if it goes through if it
tries to go through.
For the US
to say that to
like China, you know,
a Chinese tanker we're going to attack,
Yeah. it seems like a a higher bar, like
a
a a a scarier escalation and
harder to follow through on.
Isn't that
People who are actual experts, unlike
you and me, raised that very question.
>> [laughter]
>> Are you sure,
here Mr. Trump, are you sure,
you know, you want to tell both Russia
and China
that that if a tanker with their flag or
or doing their business or whatever, you
know, uh, comes near, you're going to
you're going to block it. Um,
I don't know I I get the sense that
they're kind of working
things out to defuse the blockade issue
somehow. I I you know, I don't
I don't
I don't understand what Trump is up to.
He never thinks that far in advance.
Maybe this will
put some kind of pressure on, but but
the thing that would have been easy to
do, the thing that would have oil prices
lower than they are now, which you think
would be in his interest. I mean, look,
you've got this ceasefire of a couple of
weeks where they can continue to
negotiate. That's what everybody said
when, you know, they when J.D. Vance
came out and said, "Oh, we've reached an
impasse. They can let us know whether
they accept or decline our offer or not,
you know, blah blah blah." A lot of
people said, "Look, this is all, you
know, negotiating. We'll wait and see.
We got 2 weeks. We'll see what happens."
I thought, uh,
you know, and and meanwhile, Iran did
plan to control traffic over the Strait
of Hormuz, which should have been clear
to everybody if you looked at the way
they worded their original consent to
the ceasefire, they were like, "Yes,
ships that coordinate with our military
and do XYZ." It was totally clear. They
were still going to wanted to charge
money. That was the idea.
And, you know, it would have been easy
for Trump to finesse that
you know, without losing face. He could
have said, "Look, we had thought they
were going to close down. Now we're
reading the fine print. Very sneaky of
them. Well, anyway, when the ceasefire
is over they they damn well better be
doing things our liking or there will be
held to pay." He could have done that
and then Iran would have let more and
more traffic out cuz they're making
money off of it. I think oil prices
would be lower than they are. You'd
think Trump would like that, but you
know, Trump's Trump.
Maybe
the blockade would put more pressure on
Iran. I kind of doubt it, but whatever.
You know, like
part of the problem with Trump is just
he has to generate a headline a day. You
know? Like yesterday he Where did he
attack the Pope or and So, the day
before he was Jesus, then he attacked
the Pope and I mean, it's [laughter]
just crazy.
Uh
By the way, Jesus would not attack the
Pope. Let me just You got to You should
make up your mind. Are you Jesus or are
you attacking the Pope? Why why wouldn't
Jesus attack the Pope? Well, Protestants
might say Jesus would attack the Pope,
but Catholics certainly wouldn't. Um
Catholics wouldn't, yeah.
So, uh
>> Jesus like had run-ins with the
religious authorities of his time. Like
he he was not all peace and love. He was
a contrarian. He he was uh yeah. Um
Can you imagine Trump I I I can't
remember whether he actually said this
or is this uh
me imagining based on other things he
said?
But I think he might have thrown out the
idea of doing a joint venture with Iran
and uh
you know, taking toll both of them. Mhm.
Yeah, at one point he said
>> be
Wouldn't that be a reasonable way to go
about it? A joint blockade? Well, I have
long thought that some sort of kind of
uh
implicitly [clears throat]
explicitly authorized tollgate might be
the way out of this. Cuz now Iran is
demanding reparations. Not unreasonably,
the war was in flagrant violation UN
Charter. We wiped out a ton of [\h__\h] and
may wipe out more, God forbid. Um
But you know, politically the US is not
and Israel can't say, "Yeah, we're
giving them some of our tax dollars."
But they can collect this toll. It's not
exorbitant. They're ch-
Excuse me, they're charging 2 million a
tanker. That's a dollar a barrel, okay?
The war has raised prices like 35 40 a
barrel, okay?
So, if Iran if this ongoing deal
of Iran collecting tolls wound up
raising prices a dollar, two, even three
a barrel, not a huge
deal in the scheme of things compared to
where we are now. You can imagine things
where they even
Some of the money goes to Gulf states to
rebuild stuff that Iran blew up in
retaliation
for the US-Israeli attack.
You know, since the Gulf states have US
bases there.
Um
And so on. You can you can imagine all
kinds of things.
Uh and
I I I think well, Richard Haass, the
former head of the Council on Foreign
Relations, who was one of the first
people I think maybe the first person
to propose a blockade
had that as some kind of end game. Some
kind of multilaterally
controlled
port. Now, I personally think
Iran would like to control the strait
more or less alone. It's said in
partnership with Oman. Well, even if
Oman agreed to that, we know who the
senior partner would be. And let me just
emphasize, there's real virtue in that
because
Iran needs a
lever that doesn't involve blowing [\h__\h]
up, okay? That's our in our interest. I
mean, they have signaled that if that if
Israel attacks them again, America
attacks them again, that that they
imperil the global economy, okay?
We get that point.
They they and they feel they need it
because who would trust a piece of paper
with Donald Trump's or you know, whose
signature? I mean, seriously. There's no
way to guarantee People talk about, you
know, "Well, we'll just agree to not
attack them." What the [\h__\h] are you
talking about? You literally attacked
them while negotiating with them, okay?
>> Right. Right. Right.
>> It's just It's just the inability of
American foreign policy people to put
themselves in the shoes of of any
adversary is completely mind-blowing.
But in this case,
Iran feels they need a lever like no
piece of paper's going to do it. They
need something they can do to you
if if Israel attacks. And I would rather
that thing be
just shut down traffic to the strait.
Oil prices go up than start firing
missiles at at at Israel and UAE and
Saudi Arabia, okay? That's like a good
thing from [clears throat] our point of
view, if you ask me, because Iran is
absolutely going to demand some
reassurance
that they're not going to get attacked
again. I'd rather that involve
peaceful levers. Now, in the long run,
you know, you do you would like to bring
all this whole thing back into
compliance with international law, maybe
through creation of some international
body, whatever. But we are in no
position to complain about violations of
international law. I'm sorry.
We attacked them
illegally and that's why we have a
problem here.
So, But do you see this happening? Why
like why can't that happen? Iran
controls the strait and takes the toll
and you know, gives 25% to Trump,
whatever the current price of the
passage is.
And everybody's happy. I mean, Trump is
happy and
>> think it might be a political problem
for Iran, domestic political problem to
say we're giving some of this money to
America. I don't know about that part.
But look, I the basic idea of
formalizing a tollgate that benefits
mainly Iran monetarily, I like. You
know, and I just want people to
understand that right now we're trying
to bring the the world back from the
brink of
of crude disaster of some kind, economic
and or
military.
Um
Not a bad thing for Iran to have this
peaceful form of leverage. It's
coercive, maybe it's thuggish, but it
doesn't involve missiles, okay? If they
if they can just shut shut the gate. And
I mean, behind it is the threat of of
missiles and drones. I mean, that's
that's what people know they can do to
tankers.
Uh and in a certain sense, I will say
they would maintain that in any event,
but
that's where we are on that. On the AI
front,
uh you know, as a lot of people heard,
Anthropic has this new model. They
haven't released it because it's so
dangerous. Some people say this is
marketing hype. I think mainly it's not,
I'm afraid and and that's actually
pretty clear.
It may be somewhat marketing hype the
way they're presenting it, but I don't
think there's any doubt
that the new model is of unprecedented
power and does have the capacity to find
and exploit vulnerabilities that were
previously undetected in major operating
systems, browsers, and so on. So,
Anthropic is now, without releasing it,
making it available to the companies
that maintain these pieces of
infrastructure,
Google, Microsoft, Cisco, and so on.
And they say they're going to
not release it until they can figure out
a way to find it to do so safely. Um By
the way, my The the danger is to just to
pinpoint if they release it, if I get
access to this, then I can use this
model to hack a website.
Uh or A hack a website would be to put
them on I mean, in the extreme scenario,
Nikita would be ruling the world.
I mean, I don't I don't mean you really
could use this tool that way, but
if you were mad I mean, let's say that
in Anthropic they had this thing in that
company and Dario decided he wanted to
to like bring down the world economy or
do something major.
Mhm. They could probably do that with
this tool. I I think they probably
could. I mean, they could Who knows?
Maybe blind networks of satellites, take
down whole power systems,
uh steal [snorts] everyone's browsing
histories, everyone's credit cards.
Um
I think if you had exclusive access to
this tool and a team of people really
understood the [\h__\h] yeah.
You know, that kind of bad actor.
Um
And I would imagine that even a lone bad
actor or small rogue group of non-state
actors who knew what they were doing
could do real damage. I mean, that's the
that's what we're facing, you know, I
uh you know, I I guess I'll be ritually
plugging my AI book, The God Test, until
it comes out in June. You know, and I
get into this that, you know, this is
part of the argument behind
This is one reason this stuff has to be
governed
internationally. It's you know, we
No country is safe until it knows that
no such tool is running loose in any
state, in any nation. And
uh
So, What What do you see as
the most probable scenario if it
this kind of tool does not become
available to everybody, to rogue agents,
and but it is available to Anthropic
itself. Similar tools are being
developed by other AI companies.
>> Yeah. Where does that lead if
uh the controls are in place, but it's
just a ton of power in in a few hands.
That's what
some people have been warning about. I
mean, including me, but also like the
pause people, you know? Right.
>> Um and
and look, I don't think that's crazy.
I mean, one of my main sermons is just
about
we have to do this internationally
because whatever we do, including pause,
that has to be done internationally
because if if you say to the American AI
companies, "Hey, how about a pause?"
They'll say, "No, we can't because of
China."
And China doesn't want to pause as long
as we, you know, and so on. So, uh
anyway, yeah,
it's inevitable that you're going to get
more and more super powerful things. In
fact, this model
OpenAI, everyone says, is going to have
a model about this powerful in a matter
of months, if [clears throat] not weeks,
because this is just
this model was trained on the on the
Nvidia Blackwell chips, the first model
trained on them.
And as a result of that and then the
number of those chips used and so on and
the amount of training they
it has apparently 10
trillion parameters. Now,
my sense, you don't know for sure
because they don't release the parameter
count on proprietary models. My sense is
that's like a tenfold increase, okay?
Parameters is the number of
interconnections among neurons. Neurons
are these, you know,
it's ultimately all math. They're
they're these mathematical constructs,
but they're nodes in the flow of
information through the model.
And so, there are 10 trillion
neuronal interconnections. And uh
uh you know, OpenAI is going to have one
soon. Google's going to have one before
long. I don't know if they'll train it
on Blackwell per se, but
uh
this is where it's going. And you know,
by the way, this model apparently does,
you know, extraordinarily well on a
number of benchmarks as far as we can
tell. You know, I'm sure I'm sure
Anthropic is releasing those results
selectively, but the people who know are
saying, "Yeah, very appreciably more
powerful."
So, what happens then when when these
companies have this power? Like, is that
scenario itself, without the rogue
agents entering the picture, is that
worrisome and in in what way?
>> worrisome that whether this got out of
control,
and it may have, who knows how good
Anthropic security is,
you know, who knows whether somebody has
stolen the weights,
uh but I think it's a little alarming
that the question of whether this turns
into a huge disaster for the world
depends on A, questions like that. Like,
how good's their security?
We don't I don't know. I mean, we don't
There's no There's no
meaningful regulations as far as I know
that actually involve
uh we, the people, certifying,
validating that security is good. A and
B,
>> powerful system that can can break into
other systems should be able to protect
itself, too, right?
Well,
in the long run, but remember,
it's way it came into existence before
it could have been used to secure
itself. I mean, you're talking about the
whole security system surrounding the
Anthropic lab.
And but but the other thing is, you
know, we're relying on the character of
Dario Amodei. He, you know, and he seems
like a person of, I think, true
conscience, we can say, and Anthropic
uh maybe more than most tries to do the
right thing. Fine, but
the idea that the fate of the world, we
are so reluctant
to actually enact any policy of any
consequence whatsoever at the national
level, even let alone the international
level, that we're just hoping these guys
are great guys.
Like Dario, Sam, Demis, I hope they turn
out to be great guys or, you know, but
just in case, goodbye. It's been fun
knowing you, you know? This is [\h__\h]
nuts.
This is [\h__\h] nuts. And
you know, and one
I mean, it's interesting that we're
distracted by war at this moment. That's
one reason this has gotten a lot of
attention, but
not as much as it deserves. And
>> Mhm. Anyway, but fortunately, Nikita's
big idea this week is going to save us.
How does that work, Nikita?
>> Right. Right, let's tie the two things
together, war and AI.
Uh
So, here's one way to get into this.
You've been saying this,
uh
AI poses a lot of threats.
Uh they can't be addressed on a national
level. It has to be at an international
level.
Um
And here's a critique of that position.
When you start talking about threats and
you uh
bring this up to people in charge of the
powerful technology, that puts them in
the mindset, as you've been complaining,
you know, China has been developing this
and, you know, we have to be ahead.
Same with like nuclear weapons, you
know, you're you're if you're in a race
to develop a more powerful weapon, even
if you understand that the development
of that weapon poses threats to the
entire planet,
you know, better you have it than the
adversary or a potential adversary. Even
with COVID, like that was the most
straightforward like global problem,
like we should really come together and
solve this.
Uh you know, it had the opposite effect
as well, where countries closed their
borders, protected their vaccines. Like,
we're going to We don't trust yours,
we're going to sell ours.
Uh because it's a mindset of
you know, you're threatened. You're
We're talking about threats, so I'm
going to
uh try to protect myself and see whether
I can be more powerful than whoever is
there is in the competition.
So, my proposal is
turn this around. Instead of saying we
have to address AI on an international
level because of these threats, let's do
a positive vision.
Hey, let's work together on an AI
project
that would solve things that we're
currently not able to solve very
effectively, such as all of these
conflicts, all of these wars going on.
And it seems to me that mediation
is
in principle a kind of algorithmic
like it can be solved algorithmically.
You can It's It's It can be seen as a
puzzle, as a as a math problem, as a
game theory problem. You know, you have
two adversaries, they're fighting.
Each has Each side has reasons to
continue fighting. Here's what they're
getting out of continuing the war.
Here's what they're trying to avoid by
continuing the war.
Here are their, you know, There are all
these inputs that you can put into a
system.
And a sufficiently smart system would
come up with a bunch of scenarios like
deals. Like Trump was saying, you know,
"I've been doing deals my whole life.
I'm just good at this. I'm going to
solve all these wars because I'm great
at doing deals."
Turns out that was a little bit of no
overestimation. Um
but the theoretical, like if there is a
thing that is just very good at
computing, coming up with
best-case scenarios for the parties
involved,
uh wouldn't that be a like it
can be an effective
uh
you know, algorithmic tool. An AI system
that has If you give it enough
information, if it's trained on enough
cases,
it might just be good at presenting
these
uh scenarios that are most beneficial to
uh the different sides.
And
you can imagine incentive structures
where being a part of that project, both
on the creation of it side and on using
the thing, you know, get on this thing
early and you get a benefit if if
uh you manage to finish
a conflict that's been simmering or uh
going like, you know, maybe Armenia and
Azerbaijan, like they've been
trying to stop fighting and not
uh
not
uh you know, diminish the chance of the
war restarting. Mhm. Uh they seem to be
going in that direction.
They've It's been years of
arguing about specific wording in
different points of this agreement.
Um
They
They would be happy maybe to use
the system that is trying to grow and
get more, you know, clients.
Uh
And and you use You You start with with
some like I mean, maybe you start even
smaller. Maybe it's like a scenario, you
know, it starts out as a little startup
that builds on uh small cases of like
business disputes and just trains its
muscle on like figuring out these
puzzles in lower stakes So, would this
be binding arbitration? They would agree
in advance to accept the verdict,
perhaps by virtue of the idea that,
"Okay, this is not humans.
This is not
So, we don't have to worry about the
adjudicatory panel being biased in favor
of the US uh in turn by virtue of the
US's inordinate influence over this
particular international institution.
This is a an objective arbiter, and so
both parties agree in writing, you know,
and swear on you know, a stack of holy
texts or whatever. Um
Is that the idea? Is that the idea?
I think that's unlikely to happen. I
What
I'm saying is
>> happen? How do you I mean, you know,
because like right now
between us and Iran, a lot of ideas are
out there.
You know, humans are good at generating
a multitude of ideas. I mean, if you
look at all the ideas generated by
the Iranian side and people partial to
that side and the American side and
people partial to it and American
magazines and Middle Eastern magazines
blah blah blah.
You have an array You could have an
array of proposals. It wouldn't be hard
to generate that. And then if if if it
doesn't have to be binding, if you're
saying there really is a zone
that would be acceptable to both,
why not just do that?
Have humans produce a spectrum of
solutions.
And you have Iran and the US say, "Okay,
I'll take this one, this one, this one."
And then see where the overlap is,
right? I mean
I don't know if I'm making my point, but
I think this is like theoretically
that's how it would go, right? And
that's what people are trying to do.
There's usually
>> I guess I'm saying we don't necessarily
need machines for that. I mean
uh
bargaining and you know, by the way, you
said you can you know, this is in theory
again theory. Well, yeah, there's a
whole literature on this
on
geopolitics from a game theoretical
point of view. Some of the pioneers were
like Thomas Schelling, one of the first
people to emphasize that war is a
non-zero sum game cuz it's often
lose-lose. Um
and
you know
So, that's that's there, but I guess
you know, my
uh
I mean, in the whole history of
humankind
the most effective and
almost only reliable and remotely just
solution to the problem of consequential
disagreement among parties
has been
in a certain sense binding adjudication.
In in a in a in a state in a nation's
court system, that's just part of the
deal. You're a citizen, you're buying
into binding arbit you know, binding
adjudication. You get accused of a
crime, these are This is a you know,
this is how we select the jury and the
judge that will decide and you just You
accept that in advance.
Same with civil suits. And there have
been, you know, some of the greatest
initiatives and in some cases
if temporarily successful initiatives in
international affairs have been binding
arbitration. Before the World Trade
Organization
fell apart
uh
recently
partly due to the influence of
America and in some cases specifically
Donald Trump, but not exclusively. Uh
There one of its pioneering features was
an actual
adjudicatory body
that could levy uh penalties. They they
were in the form of authorizing
the party found to have a just grievance
to levy punitive sanctions against
another party. So, in other words, it
wasn't like the international
governance system itself levies the
penalty, but it authorized the penalty
from one party to be exacted on the
other. And
like that was a big deal, but
it it fell apart for various reasons,
but one thing about it was it had human
judges. And
one thing you could ask is
if if if the judges were AI and and
because of that and this is a big if,
but if that inspired trust
in the parties and if it should, that's
another big if. Um
maybe that could lead to such a system
to stay intact longer. But I guess my
question to you is, if it's not binding
arbitration, what is the innovation
here? Like
>> first
Yeah, so first let me say I think I
misunderstood your question when you
asked about binding. I thought you're
saying binding in advance, like before
starting the negotiation, you say that
you're going to accept the verdict. No,
that is what I'm saying. That is what
I'm saying.
>> Okay.
Yeah, I think that's going to be a tough
sell. Maybe by the you know, when the
system grows sufficiently and it has a
good track record and an army of robot
dogs with guns and stuff.
Uh it'll be
uh more powerful like that, but I think
you start with
um
uh just working on the negotiation
process. And I think AI can be
effective there
for a couple of reasons. One, uh
it's not automatic that it would there
would be more trust in AI than in human
intermediaries,
but I think if it's set up
in the right way
uh
like it's an international project. It's
not an you know, an American company
that's giving you this solution, but
anybody any country can join and send
their you know, computer people to work
on this and and diplomat people to work
on this. That would be one angle. And it
you know, needs to be transparent the
system itself.
Um but the By the way, these systems
tend not to be, but I mean, large
language models
well, that's a whole complicated
question the degree of transparency. By
the way, that's another alarming thing
about Mythos I might get into. They kind
of screwed up the training, so it's less
transparent than it might be. It was
just a mistake. And now it's here. They
they they they've done this you know,
they've put all this money into it. It's
not like they can just let's do it
again.
And and they [\h__\h] up. They they didn't
Maybe we'll get into the details in
overtime. But this is what I mean. It's
like Oh well, we're trusting you.
Whatever you [\h__\h] up, the world's
going to end. Oh well.
Whatever.
Anyway.
Um
yeah, let's let's talk about this in
overtime. But what I was saying is I
think
the reason AI may be more effective in
mediation is I mean, what you're having
now when you have these rounds of
negotiations
it's teams of people that meet
you know, if it's going well every
couple of weeks.
You know, Ukrainians are talking to the
US, Russians are talking to the US, then
they go in between. It's
uh
many hours of human-to-human
interactions where emotions are present,
the stress of the other side is present.
And you know, you do this whatever
8-hour session.
And there's little communication, then
there is they go between the there is no
the process is slow, it's step by step
and uh it's
uh there's a lot of mistrust on at every
step and misinterpretation
and misrepresentation
of the positions.
Uh you know, they misunderstood what we
agreed to. kind of thing.
With AI it's going to be like
>> characteristic of Trump. I mean, if you
do it the Obama way where you actually
have veteran negotiators, you wind up
ironing all that out. But but and it
doesn't and and you don't get these huge
obstacles in the meantime the way you do
with Trump. Like, "Oh,
I thought it didn't include Lebanon. Um
Lebanon's a like a significant country.
Maybe you should have worked that out in
advance." Anyway, go ahead.
Yeah.
Uh but so what I'm imagining with this
scenario is instead you have a team of
people working with the system
at home at the computer
negotiating moving it's like a you know,
a game you're playing. You're you're
trying to get a better deal for
yourself. Mhm. And it's not the slow
step by step who's going to call whom
first. It's a process has started. And
your team is every day people show up to
work and they work with the system
trying to get a better deal and the
process
is only ever finished if
uh the two sides do reach
an agreement, but it can be
you know, continuous. A lot of the work
in computing the thing coming up with
like, "Okay, we got new input from the
Ukrainian side.
Uh let's uh
mash this with the input we got from the
Russian side.
Come up with a bunch of suggestions.
This is is sent to both sides. Another
round of negotiation and the computer
acts network as an intermediary trying
to just accelerate the process of
finding a solution that's written down
in plain language uh in you know,
legalese kind of
uh formulations.
So, basically accelerate the
the process which is what AI is good at.
Like workflows
uh
just getting
faster with this. Like it when when I'm
talking to computer program or what I'm
what I'm seeing in my own work
what I'm
my relationship with Claude Code is I'm
trying to develop
you know, workflows, loops, steps of
Mhm.
>> action where
a lot of the complicated stuff can be
done by the computer itself and then
when it needs my input is when it you
know, asks for it. But because a lot of
the work is done by the computer and
because
we're getting better like I'm trying to
get better at developing these workflows
themselves, these cycles of operation,
it just becomes way faster.
And so, if there is a deal to
be struck,
uh
it seems like just that negotiation
process can be sped up significantly
with a a smart system. Mhm. Okay, so
before I reply to all that, and also
before I explain the the
the unfortunate lack of an unplanned
uh lack of transparency in Anthropic's
new model and apparently irreversible
lack of transparency. Um
the why don't we go into overtime,
which is available to paid subscribers
to Nonzero Newsletter. There's a link in
the show notes. You can go to the
nonzero.org site. Uh where, by the way,
there's also a piece that I posted
last Friday on the connection a
different kind of connection between the
Iran war and the Mythos thing. Um
and
uh you know, and also
you can go to that you can leave
comments in a couple of places on
YouTube, but you can also leave them uh
on the under the video on our site. And
that tends to be, you know, a more kind
of unified cohesive conversation when
that when that develops. And that now
that is
available to paid subscribers.
And that's one reason it's it's you
know, pretty civil and and and and
unified and cohesive. Um but uh so we
encourage people to
do that, to become Nonzero full-fledged
Nonzero members. You know, and also we
like to think that our mission is worth
supporting. Anything And then so Nikita,
before we talk about other things we're
going to talk about in overtime,
anything you'd add to that?
We should also mention that the paid
subscribers get 50% discount on how many
newsletters is it now? Seven? Uh well,
let's see. There's uh
You tell me if I forget any. There's
uh
Foreign Exchanges, Derek Davison's um
Peter Beinart's newsletter, Paul Bloom's
Small Potatoes newsletter, Glenn Loury's
[snorts] newsletter, Mark Lilla
Goldberg's
Global Dispatches,
and
>> Seneca by Kaiser Kuo. Oh yeah, yeah.
Uh so all of those have a paid option.
And if you're a paid subscriber to
Nonzero,
you can get a a 1-year subscription at a
50% discount to any of them. Details on
the homepage of nonzero.org. You'll see
the
the big kind of 50% off coupon there.
Um
And so yeah, I would let's see, what
else we have time to talk to. I want to
proceed this talk about transparency
issue.
Um
maybe I say a little about one of these
uh
biographies I've been listening to. I
also list the one about Mark Twain.
Well, I'm going to I'm going to talk
about one person at least. Probably at
least at least two of the following:
John Adams, Adolf Hitler, Mark Twain,
Dennis the Savage.
I'm going to talk about at least
two of those people.
>> [laughter]
>> And find some connection between them.
Um I want to hear about Hitler.
Yeah, the the uh
Hitler the Hitler Twain can now is
Hitler is is sui generis. Um
okay, [laughter]
so
hope you'll follow us into overtime, but
if you even if you don't, thanks for
following us this far.
Now we go into overtime.